<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Foure and twenty certaine godly rules</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1640</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11183</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21448</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S504</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22532983</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22532983</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25599</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11183)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25599)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1756:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Foure and twenty certaine godly rules</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p., [1] leaf of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>ca. 1640]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁸ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: stained, with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Biblical teaching --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25599:1"/>
            <head>FOURE AND TWENTY Certaine Godly Rules.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>Seeke the Lord, and he will be found.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <list>
               <item>1<seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hinke and looke on eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day, as the laſt day of thy life: therefore ſo live every day, and walke before God ſo warily, as if it were the day of thy death, and thy day of Iudgement: and as if be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore night, thou wert to give an account of thy life before the Iudge of Heaven and Earth.</item>
               <item>2 In what place ſoever thou art, in thy houſe or abroad, in thy bed, or at thy boord, whether by night, or by day, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever thou art doing, ſet God alwayes
<pb facs="tcp:25599:2"/>
                  <figure/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25599:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25599:3"/>
before thine eyes: thinke that God ſées thée; and let the feare of him kéep thee from ſinne, and guide thée in the wayes of holineſſe, <hi>Pſal. 16.8.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3</hi> As ſoone as thou awakeſt, when thou firſt openeſt thine eyes in a morning, lift up thy heart to God, in thankfulneſſe to him for thy preſervation that night paſt: and doe the like at night for the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the day; thou knoweſt not any night, but it may be thy laſt night: conſider, ſléepe is compared to death, and the bed unto the grave, and thou mayeſt ſleep thy laſt ſléep, <hi>Luk. 12.20.</hi> Let this be thy laſt thought upon thy pillow, <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending thy ſelf into the hands of God.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4</hi> See that thou neglect not thy ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne, and ſet times of prayer, humbling thy ſelfe upon thy knees, firſt in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning as ſoone as thou art ready, before thou enter upon any worke, commending thy ſelfe, and all thy wayes unto God, and laſt at night, when thou goeſt to bed, kneeling at thy beds ſide, <hi>Pſal. 55.17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5</hi> Taſke thy ſelfe every day to reade ſome peece of holy Scripture, as ſome
<pb facs="tcp:25599:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the Pſalmes, and one Chapter at the leaſt of the old or new Teſtament, ſee that thou reade heedfully for the encreaſe of knowledge, and the bettering of thy ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall eſtate, as alſo at thy beſt leaſure take time to reade ſomething out of ſome other godly booke: This thou mayſt doe either morne or evening, or both, without any let or hinderance to thy calling, <hi>Acts 17.11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6</hi> Shew thy ſelfe to be a Chriſtian, and a ſervant of God every day, by la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring diligently with thy hands in ſome lawfull and honeſt calling, knowing that he who will not worke, muſt not eate, and the idle perſon hath no right to apeece of bread, and a Chriſtian muſt have a trade or calling, <hi>Epheſ. 4.28. 1 Theſſ. 4.11. 2 Theſſ. 3.10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7</hi> As thou art following of thy calling, thou mayeſt often be lifting up thy heart to God upon every freſh occaſion; This is one way of praying continually, as it is exhorted, <hi>1 Theſſ. 5.17.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8</hi> Labour to be acquainted daily more and more with the Law of God, the ten
<pb facs="tcp:25599:4"/>
Commandements: get ſome godly book that may expound them fully, that thou mayſt ſée what is ſinne, and what is not ſinne in every action: by this means thou mayeſt daily learne how <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o ſhun moe ſins, and to performe mo duties, <hi>Pſalm. 19.7. Pſal. 119.104. Jam. 5.25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9</hi> Take heed of ſinning againſt know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and of entertaining at any time a purpoſe or reſolution to ſinne in any acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for a true faith and purpoſe of ſinning againſt knowledge and conſcience can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver hold together: and ſuch ſinnes harden the heart, and in time may give a man up to a reprobate ſenſe, <hi>Rom. 1.28. 1 Tim. 1.19.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10</hi> Make conſcience as much of idle, vaine, and ungodly thoughts, as of idle and unſavoury words, or of ungodly actions conſidering that with God, who ſees and knowes the heart, idle thoughts and vain imaginations are ſinnes, as well as ſinfull words, or ungodly actions: and ſecret thoughts ſhalbe brought to Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Gen. 6.7. Eccleſ. 12.14.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11</hi> Strive daily to ſee and feele that
<pb facs="tcp:25599:4"/>
ſinfull originall corruption that thou bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt about thee, how it dulls thee, and makes thee backward, and untoward to good, and how it inclines thee, and makes thee prone unto evill: grone under it, and bewaile it, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did, <hi>Rom. 7 18, 19, 23, 24.</hi> And let thy ſinfull nature trouble thee, as well as groſſe and actuall ſinnes: and being burthened with it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take thy ſelfe to Chriſt, and deſire God on thy knees for Chriſts ſake to pardon it.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12</hi> Strengthen thy ſelfe every mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning by a firme purpoſe, and reſolution againſt thy ſpeciall ſinnes and luſts, to which by nature thou art moſt prone and ready to fall into, as pride, anger, cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſſe, and the like: Argue and reaſon with thy ſelfe in this, or the like manner, ſhall I be proud? then I ſhall ſurely fall, and God will count mee his enemy, for <hi>God reſiſts the proud, <hi>Iames 4.6.</hi>
                  </hi> Shall I be angry? If I let paſſion in, I cannot keepe Satan out; nay, by anger I ſhall <hi>grieve the holy Spirit of God, Epheſ. 4.30, 31.</hi> Shall I bee covetous? then I muſt needs bee exceeding ſinfull, for the
<pb facs="tcp:25599:5"/>
deſire of money is the root of all evill <hi>1 Tim. <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13</hi> Yet becauſe thou canſt not of thy ſelfe ſhunne, and avoid theſe ſinnes, thou muſt daily goe to God for ſtrength, for he hath promiſed to give thee ſtrength a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, if thou wilt beg it of him. Call for the power of Chriſts death, and the vertue of his Reſurrection to mortifie thy luſts, that is, to kill and ſlay ſinne in thee, and to quicken in thee all the graces of the Spirit. Call and pray that he may ſprinkle pure water upon thee, to clenſe thee from the filthineſſe and defilement of every ſinne, and that he will cauſe thee to walke in his wayes, to doe his Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements, <hi>Ezek. 36.25.27.</hi> By this means thou ſhalt every day ſomewhat weaken thy ſinnes. Then ſee thou doe it every day, that thy ſoule may reape benefit thereby.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14</hi> Doe not raſhly enter upon any courſe of life, nor performe any action whatſoever it be, whether in thy calling, or in thy recreation, before thou be certi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied concerning it, and be ſure it be not ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full,
<pb facs="tcp:25599:5"/>
but an action very good and lawfull: for hee that doubteth whether a thing be lawfull or no, and yet adventures on it, is condemned for ſin, <hi>Rom. 14.23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15</hi> If at any time againſt thy purpoſe, or reſolution thou be overtaken with any ſinne, great or ſmall, be ſure thou doe not lye, nor continue in it, but haſte unto Chriſt, with griefe and ſorrow for it, and ſo recover thy ſelfe by timely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: and never reſt till thou canſt finde thy conſcience ſatiſfied and paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied, and that is, when thou feeleſt in thy ſoule a ſpirituall hatred againſt that ſin, and an earneſt deſire and care to ſerve, and pleaſe God better, I ſay, when thou haſt ſinned, thou canſt not bee at true peace within thy ſelfe, untill thou haſt got thy heart to mourne for that ſinne, and findeſt thy ſelfe to hate it in thy ſoule, and that thou art excéeding carefull to avoid it, <hi>2 Cor. 7.11.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16</hi> Labour to be content with thy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, whether it be poverty, or ſickneſſe, or what eſtate ſoever: remember alwayes that to be the beſt condition wherein God
<pb facs="tcp:25599:6"/>
hath placed thee, for all things worke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether for good to thoſe which love God. Poverty, ſickneſſe and afflictions, are but rods, and gentle corrections to ſcourge thee for ſin, and to purge corruption out of thee, <hi>Rom. 8.28. Philip. 4.11, 12. Heb. 13.5.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17</hi> When any croſſe befalls thee, ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to finde out thy particular ſinne, which hath brought that croſſe upon thee, and neither grieve, nor weepe ſo much for the croſſe, as for the ſin which hath cauſed it, ſo turne thy worldly into godly ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, <hi>Job 13.26. 2 Sam. 16.10. 2 Cor. 7.9, 10.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18</hi> When any good thought or moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ariſeth in thy heart, doe not let it die and vaniſh, for ſo thou quencheſt the Spirit, but cheriſh theſe thoughts, and ſtirre them further up in thee by prayer, reading, and meditation, <hi>1 Theſſ. 5.19. 1 Tim. 1.6.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19</hi> Bee affected with the welfare or the miſery of others, as if it were thine owne, <hi>Weepe with them that weep, and rejoyce with them that rejoyce, <hi>Rom</hi> 12.15, 16. <hi>Heb.</hi> 13.3.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25599:6"/>
                  <hi>20</hi> Love even thine enemies as Chriſt commandeth thee, get an heart to forgive them, and an heart to pray for them: be not overcome of evill, but overcome evill with good, <hi>Rom. 12.21. Matth. 5.44.18.21.25.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>21</hi> Endevor thy ſelfe to do every day, what good thou canſt to others, upon eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good occaſion, and rejoyce when thou canſt find time, and any opportunity of doing good: The more good thou doeſt, the more comfort thou ſhalt have, when thou commeſt at night to make thy accounts with God, <hi>Gal. 6.10. 1 Tim. 6.18. John 14.21.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22</hi> In doing good to others, be care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full not onely to the bodyes of poore peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple (which thou wilt bée to feed and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>léeve them, if God hath bleſſed thee with riches) but alſo to their ſoules, doe what good thou canſt to them, by teaching and inſtructing them: he that hath truly taſted of ſalvation, will ſtudy in what he can how he may ſave others and how he may pluck them as brands out of the fire, <hi>Iude 22.23.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:25599:7"/>
                  <hi>23</hi> Take héed of partaking of others ſinnes, that is, to ſée ſin committed by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, and to ſay nothing of it, when as thou mayeſt either thy ſelfe reprove it, or informe againſt it, that it may bee puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: Hee that hath felt the weight and burthen of his owne ſinnes, will be loath to encreaſe the burthen by the ſins of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, <hi>Levit. 19.17. 1 Tim. 5.22.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24</hi> Every night call thy ſelfe to a rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning how thou haſt ſpent the day, ſee what good thou haſt done, and what good thou haſt left undone, what temptations thou haſt reſiſted, and what ſinnes thou haſt committed, thou mayeſt find comfort in the good, and thou muſt repent thee of the evill, and groaning within thy ſelfe, and grieving for the ſins of the day, Call for the blood of Chriſt to waſh and purge thee from them; thus gaining peace with God, thou mayeſt lay thee downe, and thy ſléepe ſhall be ſwéet unto thée, <hi>Pſal. 4.48. Prov. 3.24. and 2 Cor. 1.12.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>Theſe are as plaine Directions as I can give for thée, who haſt béen ignorant,
<pb facs="tcp:25599:7"/>
and now would be plainly directed. Let me adviſe thee, if thou canſt, to reade; if thou canſt not, to heare them read often over unto thee, even ſo often as that thou mayeſt get them by heart, or at leaſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come very familiar with them, and the practiſe of them will be as ſweet as honey to thy ſoule; yea, thou ſhalt find a ſecret ſwéetneſſe in the practiſe of any one of them, even in mourning within thy ſelfe for thy ſecret corruptions, which the world doth not know of, thou ſhalt meet with ſuch joy, as thou would'ſt not want for all the treaſures of this world. Oh what joy then wilt thou find in obſerving them all? the practiſe of them will make thée walke with God, and he will come, and dine, and ſup with thée, he will large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expreſſe his love to thée; he will marke thee out for his owne, and ſet the broad Seale of Heaven upon thee, then ſhalt thou find ſuch cheerings of the Spirit, and ſuch gleams of joy ſhed into thy ſoule, as will raviſh, and tranſport thée with unexpected ſwéetneſſe; a carnall and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall man can never conceive it, none
<pb facs="tcp:25599:8"/>
can know it, but thoſe that have taſted of it; <hi>Eye hath not ſeene, nor eare heard, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath entred into the heart of man the things which God hath prepared</hi> (even here in this life) <hi>for them that love him, but God hath revealed them to us by his Spirit</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>1 Cor. 2.9, 10.</hi> And if thou doſt ſo love God, that thou wilt faithfully obſerve theſe Rules he will aſſuredly reveale theſe things un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee. Conſider then aright, and the Lord give thee heart to love, and practiſe them.</p>
            <trailer>EINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:25599:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
